Guide to the Albert Edward Elsen Papers SC0569
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1999-199
  - Ideas- Form in Interwar Art
    - Primitivism (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Body-Imagery (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Sexuality (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Art/Science (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Patronage (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Painting and Sculpture/Themes (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Metaphors (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Self-sufficiency & Incomprehensibility (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Abstraction (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Premises (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Objects (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Crises (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Concepts (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Truth to Material (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Artists as Victims (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Heads-Portraits (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Conservativism (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - The Object (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Space (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - The Base (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Frames (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Reliefs in Architecture (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Monuments (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Art History
    - Mechanics (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - What should an art historian be? (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - What is an art historian? (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Various Approaches (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Articles (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Sculpture 1918-45
    - Class Outline (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Ideas-Book (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Bibliography (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Vantongerloo (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Russian Constructivism (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Poles: Kobro (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Dada (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Duchamp & Dada (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Surrealism (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - ARP (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Bachaise (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Giacometti (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Lipchitz (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Picasso (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Gonzalez (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Ernst (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Moore (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Hepworth (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Brancusi (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Schlemmer (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Max Bill (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Schwiters (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Moholy-Nagy (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Laurens (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Manzu (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Bellmer (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Mirlo (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Figure (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - 16th Century Art
    - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Renaissance Review (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Michealangelo (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Mannerist Art (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Pontormo (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - State Portrait (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Late Mannerism (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Architecture (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Baroque (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Style (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Bar: Saints (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Religious Architecture (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Rococo (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Palace Architecture (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Bar Ruler (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Humanism (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Genre (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Portraits (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Still Life (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Landscapes (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Carvagg (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Rembrant (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - US Art 1945-70
    - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - NY Club (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Gorky (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Polock (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Dekooning (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Hoffman (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Motherwell (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Gottlieb (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Kline (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Color Painting (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Rothko (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Newman (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Reinjardt (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Review/Forecast (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Ancient Art
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Mechanix (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Space (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Egypt (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Mesopotamia (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Crete (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Greek Art (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Etruria (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Egypt (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Purposes of Art
    - Introduction (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Introduction II (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Art in America
    - Introduction (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mechanix: Bible (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bibliography (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Background (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ash Can (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Stieglitz 291 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Armory Show (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Armory Show Aftermath 8 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1912-30 Modern Mut. From Armory Show (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1920s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1930s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Government Art in the Roosevelt Area (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1940-57 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Abstract Art (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Symbolists (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - The Body 1945-52 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - PW Architecture (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Is there American Art? (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Romanticism
    - Introduction (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Goya (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - David (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Definition of a Period (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Landscapes (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Gros (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Delacroix (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Art and the City (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Davmier (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Portraits for the Million (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Chains of Freedom
    - Initial Research/Ideas (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Limits of Artistic Freedom (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - New Material (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Source Material/ Artists Views (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Formulation (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Historians & Psychology (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Art/Law Material Censorship (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Iconoclasm (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Marxist Freedom (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Articles (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - 19th Century (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Critics and Censorship (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Internal Constraints (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Modern Legal Rights (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Related Speech (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Unbound MSS I (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Unbound MSS II (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Unbound MSS III (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - 20th Century Painting 3
    - Introduction (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Rivers/Rausch/John (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Rauschnberg (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Johns (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Pop (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Warhol (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Lichtenstein (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Assemblage Environments (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Color-Field Painting (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Stella (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Diebenkorn (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Op Art (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Anti-Art (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Art & Technology (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Concept Art/Systems Art (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Realism (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Anti-Establishment (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Artist Today - CODA (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Modern Sculpture
    - Introduction (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Traditional Sculpture (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Premises M.S. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Rodin (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Degas (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Rosso (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Hildebrand (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Gauguin (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Lacombe (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Matisse (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Maillol (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Minne (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Lehmbruck (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Notes (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Illustrations (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Introduction (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Figure (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Abstraction (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Reliefs (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Truth >Materials (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Monuments (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Fascism (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Victim (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chronology (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Conclusions (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Modern European and American Painting
    - Review: Cubism (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Paul Klee (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Duchamp (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Dada - Overview (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Picabia (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - German Dada (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Arp (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Max Ernest (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Surrealism (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Masson (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Miro (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Magritte - Tanguy (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Dali (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Picasso (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Art I
    - Slides (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Art's Power (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Introduction (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - The Artists Profession (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Gods (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Religious Architecture (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Cathedrals (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Ronchamp (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Sacred Book (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Fleamish (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Michaelangelo (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Modern European Sculpture
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Rodin and Modern Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Figure in 1914 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Partial Figure (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Cubism (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Constructivism (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Brancusi (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Picasso (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Medieval Art
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mechanix (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Late Antiquity (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Catacombs (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dura Europe (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Christian Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Christian Architecture (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Introduction to Mosaics (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Byzantine Architecture (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Byzantine Mosaics and Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Byzantine MSS Painting (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Man in Art
    - Mechanix (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Prejudices (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Definitions (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Form, Style and Elements (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Meaning (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Purposes of Art
    - Child Art (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Landscape (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Still Life (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Portraits (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Ethics (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Humanism (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Necessity of Art (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Purposes of Art (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Exams/Problems (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Rodin's Mind
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Priorities (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Conservatism (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Principles (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Imagination (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Analytical Mind (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Mentality (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Modern American Sculpture
    - Bill of Rights (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Calder (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Noguchi (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - David Smith (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Roszak/Ferber (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Assemblage (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Oldenberg (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Segal/Klenholz (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Figure 1945 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Simple Forms (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Structure (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Earthworks (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Modern Public Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Modern Public Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Christo (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - 1957 TV Series
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Return to Eden (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - LSS & Inscape (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Art & Religion I (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Modern Religious Architecture (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Art & City (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Family of Man (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Meaning in Abstract Art (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Art History
    - Mechanics (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Religion (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Church and Temple (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - City Planning (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Art & Government (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Body & Head (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Views of Man (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Humanism & Modernism (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - The Role of the Artist (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Problems (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Source Material (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Art History I
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lecture Schedule (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Discussion/ Paper Topic (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - TA Advice (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Source Material (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2014-066
  - In Pursuit of an Image, by Theodor Roszak, 1955 Mar 16 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2016-091
  - Charles Loring Elliott (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Iconography of the Apostolic Communion #1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Iconography of the Apostolic Communion #2 (with pictures) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sebastiano Del Piombo and Michelangelo (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ART 106: Eitner Syllabus (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ART 106: Outline of Egyptian Art Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - OUTLINE: Mesopotamia (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - OUTLINE: Aegean (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ART 106: Aegean Art / Lehmann-Hartleben: Aegean Art Outline (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - ART 107: Greek Art (sculpture) Checklist of monuments (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - ART 107: Greek Art Reading List (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ART 107: Greek Art The Geometric Period Outline (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ART 107: Greek Art The Geometric Style- Lehman-Hartleben (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - ART 107: Greek Art Geometric Period - 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ART 107: Greek Agriculture Notes (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Greek Lecture (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Greek Art (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - ART 107: Greek Art: Archaic Sculpture Outline (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - ART 107: Greek Archaic Notes (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - ART 107: Transitional Style (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ART 107: The Transitional Style in Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - ART 107: Greek 5th Century Notes Sculpture (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - ART 107: Greek Art Lehmann: Classical Greek Art Outline (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - ART 107: 4th Century (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - ART 107: Hellenistic (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - NEGATIVES (red box) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Binder: Outlines (ART 106, 107, 108, 116, 117, 118, I, 66) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Binder: Outlines (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Lectures/ German Art (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Red Binder: Spring 1946 - Notes: Michelangelo, Sebastiano Del Piombo, Pontormo, Salviati (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Blue Binder: Notes (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sculpture and Painting (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - ART 118 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - ART 117 P1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - ART 116 P18 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - ART 57/117 Slides List Michelangelo (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General Medieval (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - ART 57 Schedule (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - ART 57/117 Mannerism (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - ART 57/117 TITAN slides (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - ART 57/117 Reading List II (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - ART 57/117 Reading List I (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - ART 57 Introduction (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - ART 57/117 Raphael (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - ART 57/117 Parmigianino slides (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - ART 57/117 Correggio slides (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - ART 57/117 Tintoretto slides (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - ART 108 Carolingian (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - ART 108 Slides: Carolingian (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - ART 108 Slides: Anglo-Saxon, Ottonian (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - ART 108 Slides: Romanesque architecture (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - ART 108 Slides: Romanesque sculpture (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - ART 108 Notes: Romanesque sculpture (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Gothic (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - ART 108 Late Gothic Architecture in France (Aubert) NYU Syllabus (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - ART 108 Slides: Gothic Architecture (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - ART 108 Slides: Gothic Sculpture (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - ART 108 Notes: Gothic Sculpture (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - GREEK ARCHITECTURE (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2018-009
  - Letter, Elsen to Meyer, 1994 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Picasso Leger and Braque: The Power of Painting" (tss, mss, photos) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled tss, annotated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elsen, Albert E., "The Gates of Hell by August Rodin", 1984 (Box 1)